<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Efficiency | Jay McCarthy]]></title>
  <link href="http://jeapostrophe.github.com/blog/categories/efficiency/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jeapostrophe.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-02T10:05:25-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://jeapostrophe.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jay McCarthy]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jay.mccarthy@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Optimal Shower]]></title>
    <link href="http://jeapostrophe.github.com/blog/2012/08/06/shower/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-06T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jeapostrophe.github.com/blog/2012/08/06/shower</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of my goals in life is to do things very efficiently and get a lot
done. But throughout my whole five-year marriage, my wife has always
complained about my long showers, which to her were a waste of time
and valuable water.</p>


<p>As a computer scientist and programmer, I try to use technology to
optimize my life whenever possible. In this article, I discuss how I
improved my shower times and my marriage.</p>


<!-- more -->


<p>Before I start, two pieces of background information.</p>


<p>First, in the first two weeks or so of knowing my wife, she happened to see
me brush my teeth. I left on the water while I brushed and then rinsed
off with the same stream of water. She was horrified. She told me how
it was bad to do that and referenced a Public Service Announcement
from her childhood talking about that which called it out as "wasting
Utah." (Utah is a desert with very little rain: most places where
people live get about 15 inches per year.) Based on this, I repented
and have never left on the water since. (Marriage advice: Do whatever
your wife says.)</p>


<p>Second, I&rsquo;ve heard of people who take EXTREMELY long showers, like 30
minutes to an hour. I was more in the 15 minute to 30 minute boat,
probably averaging around 20 minutes.</p>


<p>Once we lived together, my wonderful wife started making little
comments about how long my showers were. I made a few attempts to
speed them up. The first was to play a set of a few albums during the
shower so I&rsquo;d know how long it was taking. Another was to always do
the same thing so I would have a regular order of operations and thus
go a bit faster. These didn&rsquo;t really make a significant difference. I
was probably consistently at 20 minutes and never more.</p>


<p>Next, I decided that I would "time" myself, in a sense, while in the
shower. I would just count (out loud or in my head) as I was in
there. This cut off about 5 minutes on average, probably, down to
about 15 minutes.</p>


<p>Next, I went a bit further. I would count out each
shower "activity"&#8212;<wbr />such as washing my left arm, etc. I&rsquo;d give myself
to the count of five. (But when I counted to five, it probably really
lasted between 10 and 15 seconds.) This was very effective and dropped
me down to about 10 minutes per shower.</p>


<p>But I knew I could do better. I just needed some technological help to
keep me focused.</p>


<p>Here&rsquo;s the concept:</p>


<p>* Plan out every activity that you&rsquo;re going to do. I came up with 22
things on days I washed my hair and 15 for other days.</p>


<p>* Give yourself 10 seconds per activity.</p>


<p>* Have a music file that "announces" what activity you should be doing
at each time.</p>


<p>* Make it exciting by playing intense music (different music for each
activity) during the activity.</p>


<p>* End with a horrible alarm so you will get /out/ of the shower
immediately.</p>


<p>With this concept in mind, I created two MP3s:</p>


<p>* <a href="http://jeapostrophe.github.com/downloads/code/tmp/2012-08-06-shower.mp3">The Shower Song</a></p>


<p>* <a href="http://jeapostrophe.github.com/downloads/code/tmp/2012-08-06-shower-hair.mp3">The Shower Song (w/ hair)</a></p>


<p>As my background music, I used the soundtrack for Mega Man 2 for the
NES, by Capcom. For the announcer, I used the espeak system. For the
alarm, I found a horrible alarm on freesound.org.</p>


<p>With this in place, my showers are now either 2:43 (including alarm)
or 3:51 (including alarm), depending on whether I am washing my hair
on that day. Normally I have about 10 seconds of alarm while I&rsquo;m
drying off, though.</p>


<p>Whereas before, a shower would keep me comfortable and lull me back to
sleep a little, now showers are a frenetic rush as I try to get
everything done in about 10 seconds. It is exhilarating and extremely
satisfying to have so much more free time as part of my morning.</p>


<p>You can see the program I used to generate the audio here:</p>


<p><a href="https://github.com/jeapostrophe/exp/blob/master/shower.rkt">shower.rkt</a></p>


<p>I highly recommend trying this out.</p>


<p>You may be wondering what my wife thinks about this. When I first told
her my plan, I don&rsquo;t think she believed me. But then after I used it
for the first time, she just laughed at me for a while.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
